RIHAD VARIAWA

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Data Analytic

Probability & Statistics (t-tests, ANOVA), variable reduction (PCA), Segmentation/clustering techniques Advanced analytics & modeling techniques such as regression, classification, natural language processing, time series analysis: e.g. ARIMA

Develop statistical & predictive analytical models

Wealth of experience with applying advanced analytics to a variety of business situations

Decision making ability to turn analytic thinking into production code so it can be embedded in systems that deliver insights or action

Data storage and analysis tools: e.g. SQL, Hadoop, Map Reduce & Spark

Strong understanding of financial metrics & ability to leverage decisions using financials

Confortable 'working virtually' with teammates & customers around the world

Demonstrated success as a problem solver, resultoriented & self-starter

Programming Languages

Python; Scikit-Learn, TensorFlow, Keras

R

SQL

Solidity

C++

JavaScript (D3.js), HTML & CSS

Software Applications

iPython Notebook

RStudio

GitHub & GitKraken

Microsoft Azure Machine Learning

Matlab

Weka

Power BI

MS Office suite

Regulatory Reporting Frameworks

International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) International Auditing Standards (IAS)

Corporate Finance

Business Strategies Forecasting/Budgeting

OPEN-SOURCE PROJECTS

Using Python To Analyse 60 Million US Police Stops "Insights Into Important Issues We Face Today, Racism"

Loan Application Prediction Challenge

"To Predict Whether A Loan Would Be Approved Or Not" Time Series Analysis Using Python

"Helping Investors Make An Investment In A New Form Of Transportation"

EDUCATION

Postgraduate Diploma Accounting Science (CTA) - 2014 BCompt (Hons) Accounting Science - 2011 BCompt Accounting Science - 2008

LINKS

www.linkedin.com/in/rihad-variawa-7422017b https://2series.github.io https://github.com/2series rihadv021@gmail.com

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist - eSource Analytics

Jan 2017 - Present

- Domain knowledge in financial services such as quantitative finance and risk modeling, discovering the information hidden in vast amounts of data, to enable smarter decisions that will deliver even better products and features
- Created hypotheses about ways to change the renewable energy industry through new uses of data
- Researched and implemented methodologies to measure the impact of renewable energy on the environment
- Aided a healthcare provider improve their clinical trial practices by identifying congestion in diagnostic testing as a key indicator of admissions breaches
- Designed and deployed a data-driven application for a state of the art Centre of excellence in urban innovation by collecting real-time data from environmental sensors across India and deploying proprietary analytics to find unexpected patterns in air pollution

Finance Manager - Real Estate Portfolio

Feb 2017 - May 2018

- Consult with senior business leaders to translate business goals into analytical use cases and models and communicate insights back to stakeholders
- Trained a machine learning system for real estate investments & built a model that learns from data and was able to predict the median housing prices achieving 89% accuracy
- Created presentations and visualizations for communicating insights with the business
- Delivered timely and accurate quarterly financial and management accounts
- Evaluated risk factors that could adversely affect the assets and implemented procedures to mitigate exposure to risks and disclose risk information to relevant internal and external stakeholders
- Accelerated corporate compliance, operational risks and control processes by monitoring financial obligations with banks and developing credit facilities

Associate Accountant - Audit Firm

Feb 2014 - Jan 2017

- Financial service audits of: Asset Fund Managers, Trusts, Property Management Co, SPVs & telecommunication incorporating financial analysis, consolidations & reporting
- Performed a risk based approach to external audits of (private & public) clients in environments providing exposure to risk and compliance management & 2 due diligent reports contributed
- Audited, Monitored and reported by understanding key processes, internal controls, risk identification, risk analysis, responding to risks identified, sound governance & assessed adequate information, communication and monitoring of risk management activities by those charged with governance